There are 39 million people in the world
هناك 39 مليون شخص في العالم
who are blind.
مصابون بالعمى.
Eighty percent of them
80 في المئة منهم
are living in low-income countries such as Kenya,
يعيشون في دول ذات دخل منخفض مثل كينيا،
and the absolute majority
والغالبية المطلقة
do not need to be blind.
ليس لعماهم ضرورة.
They are blind from diseases
إنهم مكفوفون بسبب أمراض
that are either completely curable or preventable.
يمكن علاجها أو الوقاية منها كليا.
Knowing this, with my young family,
بمعرفة هذا الأمر، قمت بمعية أسرتي الناشئة،
we moved to Kenya.
بالانتقال إلى كينيا.
We secured equipment,
حصلنا على تجهيزات،
funds, vehicles, we trained a team,
ودعم وعربات، ودرّبنا فريقا،
we set up a hundred clinics throughout
قمنا بإنشاء مئة عيادة على امتداد
the Great Rift Valley
الوادي المتصدع الكبير
to try and understand a single question:
لمحاولة فهم سؤال واحد:
why are people going blind,
لماذا يصاب الناس بالعمى،
and what can we do?
وما الذي يمكننا فعله؟
The challenges were great.
كانت التحديات عظيمة.
When we got to where we were going,
حين وصلنا إلى حيث كنا ذاهبين،
we set up our high-tech equipment.
نصّبنا معداتنا العالية التقنية.
Power was rarely available.
كانت الطاقة نادرة التوفر.
We'd have to run our equipment
كان علينا تشغيل معداتنا
from petrol power generators.
من مولدات الطاقة البترولية.
And then something occurred to me:
فخطر ببالي أمر:
There has to be an easier way,
لا بد من وجود طريقة أسهل،
because it's the patients who are the most in need
لأن المرضى الأكثر احتياجا
of access to eye care
للتوفر على رعاية صحية للعين
who are the least likely to get it.
هم الأقل احتمالا في الحصول عليها.
More people in Kenya,
يفوق عدد الأشخاص في كينيا
and in sub-Saharan Africa,
وفي أفريقيا جنوب الصحراء الكبرى،
have access to a mobile phone
الذين يتوفرون على هواتف محمولة
than they do clean running water.
أولئك الذين يستطيعون الحصول على مياه نظيفة.
So we said, could we harness
لذا قلنا، هل يمكننا تسخير
the power of mobile technology
قوة التكنولوجيا المحمولة
to deliver eye care in a new way?
لإيصال الرعاية الصحية للأعين بطريقة جديدة؟
And so we developed Peek,
وهكذا قمنا بتطوير Peek،
a smartphone [system] that enables
[نظام] هواتف ذكية يساعد
community healthcare workers
المشتغلين في ميدان الرعاية الصحية الاجتماعية
and empowers them to deliver eye care everywhere.
ويمكنهم من تقديم الرعاية للأعين في كل مكان.
We set about replacing traditional hospital equipment,
شرعنا في تغيير التجهيزات الاستشفائية التقليدية،
which is bulky, expensive and fragile,
الضخمة والباهظة والهشة،
with smartphone apps and hardware
بتطبيقات هواتف ذكية ومعدات
that make it possible to test anyone
تجعل تشخيص أي شخص ممكنا
in any language and of any age.
بأي لغة وأي عمر.
Here we have a demonstration
هنا نشاهد عرضا
of a three-month-old having their vision
لخدج بعمر 3 أشهر يتم فحص
accurately tested using an app and an eye tracker.
نظرهم بدقة باستخدام تطبيق ومتعقب عين.
We've got many trials going on
لدينا الكثير من التجارب الجارية
in the community and in schools,
في المجتمع والمدارس،
and through the lessons that we've learned in the field,
ومن خلال الدروس التي تعلمناها في هذا الميدان،
we've realized it's extremely important
أدركنا أنه من المهم جدا
to share the data in non-medical jargon
مشاركة البيانات بلغة مبسطة
so that people understand
ليفهمها الناس
what we're examining and what that means to them.
ما الذي نفحصه وما يعنيه ذلك لهم.
So here, for example,
لذا هنا، على سبيل المثال،
we use our sight sim application,
نستخدم تطبيقنا لمحاكاة الرؤية،
once your vision has been measured,
بمجرد قياس نظرك،
to show carers and teachers
لنري الرعاة والمدرسين
what the visual world is like for that person,
كيف يبدو العالم المرئي بالنسبة لذلك الشخص،
so they can empathize with them and help them.
حتى يتعاطفوا معه ويساعدوه.
Once we've discovered somebody has low vision,
وبمجرد أن نكتشف أن أحدهم لديه بصر ضعيف،
the next big challenge is to work out why,
التحدي الموالي هو معرفة السبب،
and to be able to do that,
ولنستطيع القيام بذلك،
we need to have access to the inside of the eye.
نحتاج إلى الوصول إلى داخل العين.
Traditionally, this requires expensive equipment
تقليديا، يتطلب الأمر أدوات باهضة
to examine an area called the retina.
لمعاينة منطقة تدعى شبكية العين.
The retina is the single part of the eye that has
شبكية العين هي منطقة العين التي تتوفر
huge amounts of information about the body
على كميات كبيرة من المعلومات حول الجسم
and its health.
وصحته.
We've developed 3D-printed,
قمنا بتطوير معدات بطابعات ثلاثية الأبعاد
low-cost hardware
وبتكلفة منخفضة
that comes in at less than five dollars to produce,
تأتي بأقل من خمس دولارات لتصنيعها،
which can then be clipped onto a smartphone
والتي يمكن أن تربط لاحقا بالهاتف الذكي
and makes it possible to get views
لتتيح إمكانية النظر
of the back of the eye
إلى الجزء الخلفي من العين
of a very high quality.
بجودة عالية.
And the beauty is, anybody can do it.
والجميل في الأمر أنه يمكن لأي كان القيام بذلك.
In our trials on over two and half thousand people,
في اختباراتنا على حوالي ألفي ونصف ألف شخص،
the smartphone with the add-on clip
فإن الهاتف الذكي مع المشبك المضاف
is comparable to a camera
يشبه في أدائه كاميرا
that is hugely more expensive
باهضة الثمن
and hugely more difficult to transport.
ويصعب جدا نقلها.
When we first moved to Kenya,
حين انتقلنا لأول مرة إلى كينيا،
we went with 150,000 dollars of equipment,
أخذنا معنا معدات تقدر قيمتها ب 150 ألف دولار،
a team of 15 people,
وفريقا من 15 شخصا،
and that was what was needed to deliver health care.
وذلك كان ما احتجناه لإيصال الرعاية الصحية.
Now, all that's needed
الآن، كل ما نحتاجه
is a single person
هو شخص واحد
on a bike with a smartphone.
على دراجة بهاتف ذكي.
And it costs just 500 dollars.
وذلك يكلف 500 دولارا فقط.
The issue of power supply
مشكل الطاقة الكهربائية
is overcome by harnessing the power of solar.
تم تجاوزه بتسخير الطاقة الشمسية.
Our healthcare workers travel
يسافر عمال الرعاية الصحية لدينا
with a solar-powered rucksack
بحقيبة ظهر تعمل بالطاقة الشمسية
which keeps the phone charged and backed up.
والتي تحافظ على الهواتف مشحونة ومخزنة احتياطيا.
Now we go to the patient
نحن الآن نذهب إلى المريض
rather than waiting for the patient never to come.
بدل انتظار قدومه الذي لا يحدث.
We go to them in their homes
نذهب إليهم في بيوتهم
and we give them the most comprehensive,
ونوفر لهم الكشف الأكثر شمولية،
high-tech, accurate examination,
عالي التقنية والدقة،
which can be delivered by anyone with minimal training.
والذي يمكن إتاحته لأي كان بتدريب بسيط.
We can link global experts
نستطيع أن نربط خبراء دوليين
with people in the most rural,
بأشخاص من أكثر المناطق النائية،
difficult-to-reach places
والتي يصعب الوصول إليها
that are beyond the end of the road,
والتي توجد بعيدا جدا عن الطرق،
effectively putting those experts in their homes,
بوضع أولئك الخبراء عمليا في بيوتهم،
allowing us to make diagnoses
مما يسمح لنا بإجراء فحوصات،
and make plans for treatment.
ووضع خطط للعلاج.
Project managers, hospital directors,
يستطيع مسيرو المشاريع ومديرو المستشفيات،
are able to search on our interface
البحث على واجهتنا
by any parameter they may be interested in.
باستخدام أي متغير يهمهم.
Here in Nakuru, where I've been living,
هنا في ناكورو حيث كنت أعيش،
we can search for people
يمكن البحث عن الأشخاص
by whatever condition.
في أية حالة.
Here are people who are blind
هنا الأشخاص العميان
from a curable condition cataract.
بسبب حالة ساد يمكن علاجها.
Each red pin depicts somebody
كل دبوس أحمر يمثل شخصا
who is blind from a disease that is curable
أعمى بسبب مرض يمكن علاجه
and treatable, and they're locatable.
ومعالجته وتحديد مكانه.
We can use bulk text messaging services
يمكننا استخدام خدمات الرسائل النصية الجماعية
to explain that we're coming to arrange a treatment.
لنشرح بأننا قادمون لتدبير العلاج.
What's more, we've learned that this is something
وما هو أهم، هو أننا تعلمنا أن هذا أمر
that we haven't built just for the community
لم نقم فقط بإنشائه من أجل المجتمع
but with the community.
بل مع المجتمع.
Those blue pins that drop represent
تلك الدبابيس الزرقاء التي تسقط، تمثل
elders, or local leaders,
كبار السن أو القادة المحليين،
that are connected to those people
المرتبطين بأولئك الأشخاص
who can ensure that we can find them
والذين يمكنهم ضمان أننا سنجدهم
and arrange treatment.
ويرتبوا أمر علاجهم.
So for patients like Mama Wangari,
لذا فبالنسبة لمريضة مثل ماما وانغاري،
who have been blind for over 10 years
والتي كانت عمياء لأكثر من 10 سنوات
and never seen her grandchildren,
ولم تر قط أحفادها،
for less than 40 dollars, we can restore her eyesight.
نستطيع إعادة بصرها بأقل من 40 دولارا.
This is something that has to happen.
هذا أمر يجب أن يحدث.
It's only in statistics
إصابة الأشخاص بالعمى بالملايين
that people go blind by the millions.
لا يتعدى كونه أرقاما إحصائية.
The reality is everyone goes blind on their own.
الحقيقة أن الجميع يصاب بالعمى بشكل منفرد.
But now, they might just be
لكن الآن، يمكنهم أن يكونوا
a text message away from help.
على بعد رسالة نصية من إيجاد المساعدة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And now because live demos are always a bad idea,
والآن، ولأن العرض المباشر دائما ما يكون فكرة سيئة،
we're going to try a live demo.
سنقوم بتجربة عرض مباشر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So here we have the Peek Vision app.
لدينا هنا تطبيق Peek Vision.
Okay, and what we're looking at here,
حسنا، ما نراه هنا،
this is Sam's optic nerve,
هو العصب البصري لسام،
which is a direct extension of her brain,
والذي هو امتداد مباشر لدماغها،
so I'm actually looking at her brain as we look there.
لذا فأنا في الواقع أنظر إلى دماغها بنظري إلى هناك.
We can see all parts of the retina.
نستطيع رؤية جميع أجزاء الشبكية.
It makes it possible to pick up diseases
تجعل من الممكن أن نطلع على أمراض
of the eye and of the body
العين والجسم
that would not be possible without access to the eye,
والذي لن يكون ممكنا من دون الولوج إلى العين،
and that clip-on device can be manufactured
وذلك الجهاز المشبكي والذي يمكن تصنيعه
for just a few dollars,
بخمس دولارات فقط،
and people can be cured of blindness,
ويمكن علاج الأشخاص من العمى،
and I think it says a lot about us as a human race
وأظن أن تطويرنا للعلاج من دون إيصاله
if we've developed cures and we don't deliver them.
يقول الكثير عنا كجنس بشري.
But now we can.
لكن الآن يمكننا ذلك.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)